After Shih Lung took Taiwan in 1683,
1683 年 施 琅 攻 佔 台 灣 之 後
most Ching officials
清 常 國 的 官 員
favored abandoning the island.
大 多 數 傾 向 棄 守 台 灣
Yet Shih was opposed to such an idea.
只 有 施 琅 排 斥 眾 人 看 法
He stressed the importance of Taiwan
大 力 陳 連 台 灣 的 重 要 性
and insisted on keeping the island.
堅 持 保 留 台 灣
Shih submitted to the Ching Emperor
並 且 向 康 熙 皇 帝 上 書
his Memorial to the Emperor on the Taiwan Issue,
﹁ 恭 陳 台 灣 棄 留 疏 」
analyzing the pros and cons of keeping Taiwan.
分 析 棄 留 台 灣 的 利 害 得 尕
Shih was an ex-military under Cheng Cheng-kung
施 琅 曾 經 是 鄭 成 功 的 屬 下 將 領
who had combat experience
在 中 國 東 南 沿 海 與 台 灣 附 近
along the southeast coasts of China and near Taiwan.
有 實 際 作 戰 的 經 驗
He knew Taiwan's geographic location
深 知 台 灣 的 地 理 位 置
was crucial and could shield
對 大 陸 東 南 沿 海 四 省
the four coastal provinces in southeastern China.
安 全 屏 障 的 重 要 性
The Ching government finally accepted his recommendation
清 常 國 終 於 採 納 施 琅 建 言
to incorporate Taiwan into its domain.
將 台 灣 納 入 版 圖
Yet the Ching administration took an attitude to Taiwan,
但 對 這 座 孫 懷 海 外 的 小 島
this small island oversea,
卻 掌 取 了
that was different from its rule on the mainland.
不 同 於 大 陸 的 治 理 態 度
Afraid of losing control if immigrants increase,
清 常 國 怕 移 民 一 多 就 難 以 控 制
the Ching administration issued proclamations to place
於 是 頒佈 了 ﹁ 渡 台 禁 令 」
tight limits on immigrants.
嚴 格 限 制 移 民 的 資 格
Immigrants were not allowed to take family to Taiwan.
不 准 攜 家 常 眷 渡 台
Taiwan's officials and armies rotated every three years.
而 駐 台 官 兵 則 是 採 三 年 輪 調 制
Building of castles and walls was prohibited.
不 准 興 建 城 牆
Despite the prosperity of the Ching Dynasty,
當 時 的 清 朝 正 是 帝 國 盛 世
the restrictions on immigrants
﹁ 渡 台 祺 令 」 的 頒 布
reflected the government's attitude towards Taiwan,
反 映 了 清 帝 國 對 台 灣
that was at the empire's frontier.
這 塊 帝 國 邊 陲 之 地 的 心 態
Under such conservative rule
就 在 清 常 國 這 種 保 守 的 治 理 下
of frontier Taiwan,
邊 陲 的 台 灣
people living along coastal areas
成 為 中 國 大 陸 福 建
of Fuchien and Kuangtung
廣 東 沿 海 居 民
crossed the perilous Black Water Ditch
橫 踏 險 惡 的 黑 水 溝
in search of better lives.
尋 找 新 天 地 的 天 堂
During this period,
這 一 段 期 間
English physicist Sir Isaac Newton
遠 在 莢 國 的 科 學 家 牛 頻
had already discovered the
已 經 發 現
law of universal gravitation and invented calculus.
萬 有 引 力 定 律 與 微 積 分
Western history
西 方 國 家 的 歷 史
would be rewritten along with
隨 著 對 物 理 世 界 的 發 現
the discoveries in the physical world.
將 開 始 改 寫
Shih Lang died in 1696.
1696 年 就 在 施 琅 過 世 的
That winter,
那 一 年 入 冬 的 時 候
in Fuchou a big fire gutted the ammunition warehouse.
福 州 城 火 藥 庫 發 生 大 火
More than 500,000 kgs of gunpowder went up in smoke.
五 十 餘 萬 斤 的 火 藥 付 之 一 炸
The Fuchien grand coordinator
福 建 巡 撫
thus sent an adviser,
於 是 派 當 時 擔 任 師 幅 的
Hangchou scholar Yu Yung-he,
杭 州 秀 才 郊 永 河
to mine sulfur in Taiwan.
到 台 灣 掌 集 碌 磺
Before Cheng surrendered,
台 灣 在 鄭 氏 降 清 之 前
Taiwan had never offered tribute to the Ching Dynasty.
從 未 向 天 朝 納 貢
Neither did it have official trade relations with China.
也 沒 有 正 式 貿 易 的 往 來
But Yu found Taiwan
但 在 郊 永 河 的 心 中
to be a residence of the gods.
卻 是 神 仙 的 居 所
He recounted his travel to Taiwan in his
他 把 在 台 灣 旅 行 的 見 聞
journal Pai Hai Chi You,
寬 成 了 ﹁ 稗 海 紀 遊 」
a rare firsthand account
為 當 時 的 台 灣
of the sights and sounds of Taiwan during that time.
留 下 了 難 得 的 第 一 手 紀 錄
In the first lunar month 1697,
1697 年 正 月
Yu's fleet left Hsiamen.
郁 永 河 率 領 船 隊 由 廈 門 出 發
In the morning of the 24th day of the second lunar month
2 月 24 日 早 晨
the blue seawater turned dark.
海 水 由 深 碧 轉 為 淡 黑
The fleet arrived at Luerhmen through Black Water Ditch.
船 隊 經 遇 了 黑 水 溝 拭 達 鹿 耳 門
Upon their arrival,
清 朝 初 時 來 接 管
the small island of Taiwan,
看 作 小 小 刈 台 灣
Tainan Prefecture City, Chulo County,
台 南 府 城 諸 羅 縣
Fengshan, Huwei Harbor,
鳳 山 一 直 到 滬 尾 港
and the coastal areas inhabited Pingpu aborigines.
海 岸 攏 是 平 埔 人
Yu and his party
郊 永 河 一 行 人
on the 7th day of the 4th lunar month, 1697
在 1697 年 4 月 7 日
left Tainan Prefecture City,
由 台 南 府 城 出 發
headed north on cow-driven carts.
搭 乘 黃 牛 笨 車 起 陸 路 北 上
I came to Taiwan to mine sulfur.
我 為 了 掌 買 硫 殯 來 到 台 灣
I've stayed in the city for two months,
在 府 城 住 了 兩 個 月
buying textiles, oil, sugar,
忙 著 買 布 、 買 油 ˊ
casting woks, blades, axes, hoes,
鑄 大 鍋 子 、 打 造 刀 、 芾 、 鋤 頭
making all sizes of wooden buckets,
做 大 大 小 小 的 木 桶
and measuring devices.
製 作 秤 、 尺 、 斗 、 斛
Things are finally ready.
這 些 都 準 備 好 了
The cloths will be traded for sulfur with the aborigines.
布 是 用 來 和 原 住 民 交 換 硫 礦
The oil and woks are for processing sulfur.
油 和 大 鍋 子 是 提 煉 砸 磴 用 的
Sugar is for use as food and for bathing by the artisans
糖 是 讓 工 匠 飲 用 和 洗 滔
to cleanse sulfur toxicity.
用 來 消 除 硫 磴 毒 氣
Yu first visited
郎 永 河 首 先 經 遇
the four major communities of the Siraya tribe
分 布 在 今 天 台 南 市 一 常 的
in present-day Tainan City.
西 拉 雅 族 四 個 主 要 部 落
He changed carts upon getting to each tribal community.
毒 到 一 個 當 地 人 部 落 就 換 車
The cart was drawn by a cow
車 子 用 黃 牛 拉 著
and driven by locals.
由 當 地 人 負 責 騰 馭
Yu crossed Tachou River (Yanshui River)
當 天 遇 了 大 洲 溪 ( 鹽 水 溪 ﹚
Passing through Hsinkang commune (Hsinshih, Tainan),
經 遇 新 港 社 ( 台 南 新 市 ﹚
Chialiuwan commune (Sanhua, Tainan),
嘉 溜 灣 社 ( 台 南 善 化 ﹚
and Matou commune (Matou, Tainan).
麻 豆 社 ( 台 南 麻 豆 ﹚
Although locals lived in the areas,
雖 然 都 是 當 地 人 居 住 地
trees were luxuriant and houses were neat.
但 樹 木 繁 茂 房 屋 整 齊 清 潔
The communes were not worse than the villages in China.
不 比 內 地 的 村 落 差
Who said that the aboriginal tribes were backward?
誰 說 原 住 民 落 後
How can you believe everything
別 人 說 的 話
that other people have said?
怎 麼 脊 全 部 採 俸 吻
After crossing Pachang River,
遇 了 八 掌 溪 之 後
Yu arrived at Chulo mountain commune,
郎 永 河 進 入 諸 羅 山 社
belonging to Hoanya tribe.
這 裡 已 經 是 屬 於 洪 雅 族 的 地 界
Theirs was a different culture.
放 睦 所 見 風 土 人 物 大 不 相 同
After they had crossed the river, it rained.
過 河 後 碰 到 下 雨
They walked hastily for 15 kilometers
加 快 腳 步 走 了 三 十 里
to reach Tawu commune to spend the night.
到 達 大 武 郡 社 (彰 化 社 頭 ﹚ 遇 夜
Today, I saw
這 一 天 所 看 到 的 當 地 人
more and more locals with tattoos.
身 上 有 刺 青 者 越 來 越 多
Their earlobes were as big as bowls.
耳 輪 也 更 大 像 碗 一 般
Their hair was bound.
都 把 頭 髮 束 起 來
Some were bound into three splits or two horns.
有 的 分 為 三 個 叉 或 束 成 兩 個 角
Others made chicken feather decorations
又 以 有 三 根 雞 羽 做 成 旗 癡 狀
and placed them on their hair
插 在 髮 鬢 上 迎 風 招 展
for beauty.
以 顯 示 美 觀
On the 12th, Yu's party passed Yashu commune
12 日 經 遇 啞 束 社 ( 彰 化 市 ﹚
(Changhua) and reached Tatu commune (Tatu, Changhua).
到 達 大 肚 社 ( 彰 化 大 肚 ﹚
The uneven rocky road
一 路 大 大 小 小 的 石 頭
resulted in a bumpy ride on the cow-driven cart.
牛 車 在 石 頭 上 一 路 類 頗
The trip was exhausting.
讓 人 非 常 疲 憲
The weeds and wild trees
加 上 途 中 竟 是 荒 蕪 的 樹 林 芒 草
along the way were shoulder-height.
生 長 多 年 的 草 比 肩 膀 還 高
Compared to areas south of Changhua,
這 與 半 線 以 南 地 區 相 比
this looked like another world.
好 比 就 像 是 兩 個 世 界
Yu's party passed through the
郊 永 沼 一 行 人 經 過
Babuza tribe in Panhsien commune
位 於 彰 化 市 半 線 社 的
of Changhua City.
巴 布 薩 族 部 落
They entered Tatu and Shalu communes,
進 入 大 肚 社 、 汪 鹿 社
and arrived at Niuma commune,
接 著 來 到
present-day Chingshui area in Taichung County.
今 天 台 中 縣 清 水 一 常 的 牛 罷 社
The Papora people lived in the three communes.
這 三 社 是 帕 瀑 拉 族 的 居 住 區
It was dark and rainy on the 14th.
14 日 滿 天 烏 雪 大 雨
We couldn't proceed.
無 法 上 路
The rain stopped in the afternoon.
午 後 雨 停
We heard roaring tides
聽 到 海 上 傳 來 的 ﹁ 海 吼 聲 」
similar to those in Chientang River.
很 像 錢 塘 江 的 慇 潮 聲
The roaring continued even at night
到 暹 上 還 不 停 止
People in the commune said
社 裡 的 人 說
“The waves were signs of rain.”
﹁ 海 吼 是 下 雨 的 徵 兆 」
It rained on the 15th and 16th.
15、16 日 兩 天 都 下 雨
Ahead of us, Tachia River
前 面 溪 流 ( 大 甲 溪 ﹚
rose and was rampaging. We were afraid to cross it.
新 滿 的 水 正 湍 急 不 敢 前 進
Days of rain flooded Tachia River.
困 為 連 日 下 雨 使 大 甲 溪 暴 漲
Although in a hurry to complete his mission,
急 著 北 上 完 成 任 務 的 郊 永 河
Yu was forced to remain in Niuma commune for 10 days.
﹕ 迫 滯 守 滯 留 被 留 在 牛 罵 社 十 天
As the weather improved slightly,
等 到 天 氣 稍 微 放 晴 時
we took a risk and crossed the river.
便 冒 險 渡 過 湍 急 的 河 面
It was slightly sunny on the 17th.
17 日 稍 稍 放 晴
My bed was facing the mountain.
我 的 床 鋪 面 對 著 山
The hazy fog had blocked
E 火 鎔 史 心 鑊 ﹣ 嬰 ﹒
my view for five days.
擋 住 我 的 視 線 整 整 五 天
It was impossible to see the mountain.
就 是 沒 辦 法 看 到 睦 前 的 山 麓
So seeing the sky brighten up cheered me up.
怕 然 看 見 天 氣 開 朗 非 常 快 活
I realized that the mountain blocked
想 起 未 開 化 當 地 人 的 兇 悍
the fierce barbarians from us.
全 靠 有 這 座 山 擋 著 了
I wondered how it is like
不 知 道 山 後 的 深 山
deeper behind the mountain.
究 竟 是 什 麼 樣 子
Yu's party hurried up north.
郊 永 沼 一 行 人 趕 路 北 上
They passed Taichung Tachia's
經 遇 台 中 大 甲 的
Tachia and Shuangliao communes.
大 甲 社 、 雙 寧 社
Reaching Miaoli, they stayed overnight in Wanli commune.
到 苗 栗 苑 里 的 宛 里 社 過 夜
The Taokas people lived in the three communes.
這 三 社 是 道 卡 斯 族 的 居 住 地
After crossing the river,
自 從 渡 溪 以 後
there were uglier cart drivers.
駒 牛 車 的 當 地 人 相 貌 更 醜
Their backs were tattooed with spots like the leopard's.
胸 肩 刺 著 豹 皮 花 紋 的 刺 青
Men and women
不 論 男 女
kept very short hair
都 剌 短 頭 髮
that cover their foreheads,
覆 蓋 顒 頭
just like mendicant Buddhist monks.
好 像 頭 陀 的 樣 子
On the 26th day of the 4th lunar month,
4 月 26 日
Yu arrived at Nankan commune in Luchu, Taoyuan.
郊 永 河 披 達 桃 園 蘆 竹 的 南 崁 社
He described Nankan as full of thistles and wild grasses.
他 描 迷 南 崁 一 常 荊 棘 莽 草 叢 生
It is a lair for wild beasts
是 野 獸 的 巢 穴
and unsuitable for human residence.
實 在 不 適 合 人 類 居 住
Having passed Nankan commune,
經 過 南 崁 社 之 後
Yu's party again
郊 永 河 一 行 人
traveled along the coastline
再 度 沿 著 海 岸 前 進
and arrived at Pali commune,
到 達 現 在 的 八 里 分 社
the territory of the Ketagalan people.
進 入 凱 達 格 蘭 人 的 活 動 範 圍
Yu's party rode small boats to pass
郁 永 河 等 人 坐 著 ﹁ 艋 船 」
through the narrowest path on Tamsui River
經 過 淡 水 河 道 最 狹 窄 的 地 方
called Kantoumen,
當 時 叫 做 ﹁ 千 豆 門 」
which is present-day Kuantu in Taipei.
也 號 是 現 在 台 北 的 關 渡
Upon reaching Peitou,
前 往 北 投
Yu started to mine sulfur.
郊 永 河 在 北 投 採 集 碌 磴
Yu's party had survived diseases and storms
歷 經 疾 病 、 風 災
passed through 27 aboriginal tribes,
經 過 二 十 七 個 原 住 民 各 社 部 落
and crossed 96 rivers.
越 過 九 十 六 條 大 小 溪 流
They traveled from present-day Tainan to Tamsui.
從 今 天 的 台 南 走 到 淡 水 河 邊
After about 20 days,
共 花 了 約 二 十 天
Yu finally finished his mission in the 10th lunar month 1697.
終 於 在 1697 年 10 月 完 成 任 務
He left Tamsui
離 開 淡 水
and returned to Fuchou to
回 到 福 州 完 成 了
finish his journal of the Taiwan travel:
﹁ 褚 海 紀 遊 」 這 部 台 灣 遊 記
Pai Hai Chi You. The greatest contribution of his journal
﹁ 褚 海 紀 遊 」 最 大 的 須 獻
are records of the late 17th century
就 是 留 下 了 十 七 世 紀 末
tribes and geographies in Taiwan's west coast,
台 灣 西 海 岸 的 族 群 、 地 理 景 觀
and literary contributions to the humanities and history.
還 有 人 文 歷 史 的 珍 貴 文 獻
His journal described many scenes,
書 裡 面 描 寫 很 多 的 景 觀
phenomena, and aborigine tribes,
現 眠 與 族 群
all of which were recorded for the first time.
都 是 第 一 次 被 記 錄 下 來
Many of his descriptions, in particular those of
尤 其 是 分 布 在
the many Pingpu tribes in the west coast of Taiwan,
西 海 岸 的 許 多 平 埔 族 聚 落
are today inexistent.
今 天 已 經 無 法 再 看 得 到
Thanks to Yu Yung-he
因 為 郊 永 河
the brave traveler,
這 位 勇 敢 的 旅 行 家
we can experience Taiwan
我 們 得 以 真 實 的 慶 愚
from 300 years ago, at a time when the Han people
到 三 百 年 前
did not migrate in large numbers to this island.
漢 人 還 沒 大 量 渡 海 來 台 之 前 的 台 灣
Going to Taiwan from China,
唐 山 遇 台 灣
one feels extreme apprehension.
心 肝 結 歸 丸
Half of those who go to the hinterlands could exist on,
遇 番 存 一 半
but none of those who go to Taiwan are ever seen again.
遇 台 灣 無 底 看
I am Peng Jui-jun from Lufeng in Huichou, Kuangtung.
我 是 廣 東 惠 州 陸 豐 人 彭 瑞 潤
Because the administration prohibited
困 為 官 府 禁 止
the Kuangtung people
我 們 廣 東 人 去 台 灣
from bringing their family to Taiwan,
又 禁 止 攜 帶 家 眷
I asked my relatives to smuggle
我 們 一 家 老 小 九 人
my nine family members to Taiwan.
只 好 託 親 嫉 幫 忙 偷 渡
At that time, Taiwan still had vast areas of land
台 灣 當 時 還 有 許 多 土 地
that remained idle.
沒 有 被 開 壅
To poor farmers living along coastal areas in Fuchien and
對 福 建 廣 東 沿 海 的 貧 困 農 民 來 說
Kuangtung, despite all kinds of danger crossing the sea,
雖 然 渡 海 來 台 充 滿 各 種 危 險
Taiwan was their only chance
台 灣 卻 是 他 們
to improve their lives.
唯 一 可 脊 改 變 命 運 的 地 方
The Hakka immigrants came mostly from Kuangtung.
客 家 移 民 大 多 數 來 自 廣 東
The trials and tribulations of the early Hakka immigrants,
描 寫 客 家 先 民 渡 海 來 台
the contents of the ballad Tu Tai Pei Ko,
這 段 血 淚 史 的 ﹁ 渡 台 憎 歌 」
were written
是 早 期 客 家 來 台 先 民
by the early Hakka immigrants.
所 創 作 的 歌 謠
To this day,
直 到 今 天
the ballad remains popular in Taiwan.
仍 然 在 台 灣 民 間 傳 唱 不 已
Waves after waves
一 群 接 著 一 群
of coastal residents in China
充 滿 冒 險 精 神 的 大 陸 沿 海 居 氏
bribed officials or became stowaways
以 資 賂 官 員 或 是 偷 渡 方 式
in their attempt to come to Taiwan.
紛 紛 離 開 家 鄉 奔 赴 台 灣
At that time, the Ching administration was focused on
當 時 清 政 府 對 台 灣 的 政 務 重 心
preventing rebellion in Taiwan.
一 直 擺 在 防 範 叛 亂 上
Consequently, the exodus from Fuchien and Kuangtung
翳 於 福 建 廣 東 的 移 民 潮
was not managed with much enthusiasm.
不 但 沒 有 積 極 管 理
The administration instead set many restrictions.
反 而 設 下 重 重 限 制
Yet the restrictions were unable to curb
但 是 官 府 的 禁 令 仍 然 無 法 阻 擋
the people's desire to cross the sea.
人 民 出 海 的 慾 莘
Hence, illegal immigration along the coastal areas
於 是 大 陸 沿 海 偷 渡 風 潮
became rampant.
缽 行 一 時
Although illegal immigrants faced dangers at sea,
雖 然 偷 渡 必 須 面 對 洶湧 的 海 浪
the danger was nothing compared with snakeheads.
卻 比 不 上 浯 途 ﹁ 客 頭 」
The atrocities the snakeheads inflicted on the illegal
對 於 偷 渡 者 的 迫 害
immigrants was the scariest.
更 令 人 害 怕
The snakeheads were like now's human trafficking gangs
﹁ 筆 頭 」 就 是 今 天 的 人 蛇 集 團
Illegal immigrants often
偽 ﹣ 測 者 常 常 會 遭 6 N 庶
fell victim to these snakeheads.
﹁ 筆 頭 」 的 種 種 迫 害
If during the trip,
航 海 期 間 偷 渡 的 人
immigrants had disputes over money
姜 果 困 為 錢 財 等 事 情
with the boat owner,
和 船 東 發 生 爭 基
they would be thrown overboard.
就 會 被 推 下 海 ﹁ 灌 水 」
Other immigrants could only watch
有 時 引 須 眼 睜 睜 看 著 偷 渡 者
as those thrown overboard drowned
被 海 浪 沖 走
and were eaten by fishes.
﹁ 饗 魚 」
Sometimes, the snakeheads
或 者 被 ﹁ 客 頭 」 騙 到 近 岸 邊
would leave the illegal immigrants
讓 人 自 行 登 岸
on their own at the beach.
﹁ 放 生 」
A popular saying from that time was: Six died,
當 時 流 傳 下 的 俗 語 還 有
three were stuck, and only one was able to return.
﹁ 六 死 三 留 一 回 頭 」 的 說 法
It described the hardship of Chinese immigrants to Taiwan.
道 盡 唐 山 過 臺 灣 的 移 民 心 聲
It also described how
說 明 移 民 台 灣 的 人
only less than one-third of the immigrants
幾 乎 只 有 三 分 之 一 不 到 的 比 率
were able to survive in Taiwan
在 台 灣 定 居 生 存
while most died.
大 部 份 人 遭 遇 死 亡
Because survival was not easy,
少 數 人 困 為 生 存 不 易
a few were forced to return to the mainland.
又 被 迪 返 回 大 陸
Despite atrocities by the snakeheads
即 使 遭 到 ﹁ 客 頭 」 的 迪 害
and dangers of the Black Water Ditch,
甚 至 面 對 黑 水 溝 險 惡 的 海 象
the Han immigrants were undaunted
也 無 法 攔 阻 這 批 漢 人 移 民
in their search for a better life.
逄 求 美 好 生 活 的 決 心
These waves of immigrants
一 波 波 的 移 民 潮
would proceed to change Taiwan's history.
也 將 台 灣 推 向 墩 史 新 頁
The early immigrants
早 期 來 台 的 移 民
needed to apply for permits
需 要 先 向 政 府
from the government
申 請 閔 墓 許 許 可 執 照
in order to cultivate ownerless lands.
才 能 開 始 拓 壅 沒 有 主 人 的 土 地
After gaining possession of the land,
取 得 土 地 所 有 權 後
they must pay taxes regularly.
于 須 定 期 向 政 府 納 稅
This is a permit to cultivate land
這 是 1709 年 康 熙 48 年
issued by the district government of greater Taipei
大 台 北 地 區 官 府 所 發 出 的
in 1709 (the 48th year of the reign of Emperor Kanghsi).
第 一 張 准 壅 單
Obtaining the land was only the first step.
取 得 土 地 只 是 第 一 步
Developing water sources
開 發 水 源 同 樣 也 是
in a nomadic farming society
移 墾 式 社 會 發 展 過 程 中
was also essential.
最 重 要 的 命 脈
Thus, the right to develop land
困 此 土 地 的 開 發 權
was as important as the acquisition of water sources.
跟 水 源 的 取 得 同 樣 重 要
In areas where water was scarce
在 水 源 取 得 不 易 的 地 方
the Han Chinese cultivated land
漢 人 便 利 用 土 地 開 操 的 模 式
to manage water for irrigation.
來 經 營 水 利
Most rivers in Taiwan
由 於 台 灣 多 數 溪 流
were torrents
大 都 是 流 量 不 穩 定 的
with irregular water flow.
萍 溪 型 沼 川
To ensure a steady supply of water,
為 了 磐 保 水 源 不 絕
people during those days competed for water.
先 民 展 開 搶 水 大 戰
The construction of irrigation systems
水 址 的 修 築
consolidated participating villagers
也 將 共 同 參 與 的 鄉 民
into a unit that shared the same fate.
凝 聚 為 利 益 攸 關 的 命 運 共 同 體
They became more united in times of conflict of interest
遇 到 利 益 衝 突 時 也 更 加 團 結
and fought against outsiders.
一 致 向 外
With cultivation came conflicts.
壅 殖 與 械 鬥 蔓 延 的 路 線 交 疊
Conflicts occurred wherever interests were involved.
利 益 在 哪 裡 衛 突 就 到 哪 裡
In 1709, land cultivator Shih Shih-pang
1709 年 大 壅 戶 施 世 榜
set up the Papao irrigation system in Changhua plain.
在 彰 化 平 原 開 發 八 堡 址
It drew water from Choshui River in Pitsaitou,
從 二 水 的 鼻 仔 頭 引 演 水 溪 的 水
Erhshui to irrigate farms in eight blockhouses.
灌 溉 了 八 個 堡 的 田 園 水 均
The system covered most villages, townships,
範 圓 涵 蓋 今 天 整 個 彰 化 縣
and cities in today's Changhua County.
大 部 分 鄉 鎮 市
Over 12,000 hectares of land benefited from this system,
使 得 一 萬 二 千 多 甲 土 地 受 惟
during the time the largest hydraulic engineering project.
是 當 時 最 大 的 水 利 工 程
In 1760, Kuo Hsi-liu also set
1760 年 郭 錫 瑞
up a large irrigation system from Hsintien and Green Lake,
也 興 築 了 一 條 自 新 店 、 碧 潭
passing through Tapinglin, Chingmei, and Kungkuan.
經 大 坪 林 、 景 美 、 公 館
It supplied water to eastern Taipei plain.
瀚 溉 台 北 平 原 東 半 部 的 大 水 址
After nomadic farming communities
移 壅 式 社 會
developed in Taiwan,
在 台 灣 發 展 起 來 以 後
prominent family gradually emerged
漢 人 社 會 逐 漸 出 現 了
in the Han communities.
許 多 地 方 大 族
Some gained prominence due to military merits,
有 困 為 憤 藉 軍 功 而 螈 起 的
such as Wang Te-lu of Chiayi.
笙 祿
Others passed the imperial exam and became
也 有 困 由 科 舉 考 試 做 官
a government official such as Cheng Yung-hsi of Hsinchu.
而 發 跡 的 新 竹 鄭 用 錫
Cheng was the first chin-shih from Taiwan in more than 100
他 是 開 台 一 百 多 年 來 的
years after Taiwan's inclusion in the Ching Empire.
第 一 位 本 土 進 士
There was also the Lin family from Wufeng,
以 及 後 來 和 整 個 台 灣 歷 史 發 展
playing an important role
有 密 切 關 聯 的 霧 峰 林 家
To protect their own interests,
有 些 地 方 大 族
some prominent families
為 了 保 護 自 身 的 利 益
recruited and paid tenant farmers
以 大 小 租 戶 的 從 屬 關 係 為 基 礎
to become their private armies
出 資 雇 用 私 人 武 力
and created the so-called village militia,
發 展 出 所 謂 的 ﹁ 鄉 勇 團 練 」
that the Ching administration both loved and hated.
使 得 清 常 國 又 愛 又 怕
For instance, Lin Wen-cha of Wufeng
以 露 峰 林 家 的 林 文 察 為 例
led Taiwan-trained militia
他 不 但 率 領 台 勇 軍 隊
to the mainland to suppress
渡 海 參 加 圍 勦
the Taiping Rebellion.
﹁ 太 平 天 國 之 亂 」
Lin also helped the administration
也 協 助 了 官 府
suppress riots in Taiwan.
平 定 台 灣 內 部 的 動 亂
At a time when nationalism has yet to take shape,
在 國 家 意 識 還 沒 有 形 成 的
the local militia
漢 人 移 壅 社 會 中
of the Han Chinese nomadic farming community
這 種 由 地 方 武 裝 勢 力
cemented civilians
發 展 出 來 的 民 間 轟 聚 力
and fostered a sense of identity among villages.
也 強 化 了 地 域 鄉 里 的 認 同 愁
As the influence of these prominent families
這 些 地 方 大 族 的 影 響 力
increased,
逐 漸 擴 大
it started to threaten the ruling class,
終 於 威 脢 了 原 來 的 統 治 階 級
which finally led to joint suppression
難 逃 被 皇 權 官 權 和 反 對 勢 力
by imperial officials and its enemies.
聯 手 打 壓 的 命 運
In the early days of the Ching rule in Taiwan,
清 常 國 治 台 初 期
public authority was weak and corruption abounded.
公 權 力 不 彰 貪 官 污 吏 不 少
Civilians often engaged in self-help
民 間 盛 行 自 力 救 濟
to resist Ching suppression,
反 抗 官 方 的 欺 壓
resulting in frequent civil unrest.
困 此 很 客 易 成 為 ﹁ 民 變 」
Immigrants of different ancestral origins organizing
另 外 不 同 祖 籍 的 移 氏
village fraternities for mutual assistance
組 成 同 鄉 團 體 有 事 互 相 救 援
were also involved in frequent conflicts
也 會 常 常 會 常 常 困 為 衝 突
that resulted in armed violence.
而 造 成 不 同 族 群 間 的 ﹁ 械 鬥 」
The society during that time
使 得 當 9 晶 當 時 的 台 灣 社 會
was full of violence.
充 滿 了 暴 戾 之 氣
Armed violence and civil unrest
﹁ 械 鬥 」 加 上 ﹁ 民 變 」
led to a major social confrontation
造 成 台 灣 平 均 每 五 年
once every five years
就 會 發 生 一 次 大 壅 的 社 會 衝 突
until finally the largest
最 後 終 於 爆 發 了
revolt against the Ching rule erupted.
第 一 次 大 規 模 的 抗 清 事 件
Chaos under the Ching rule caused civilians sufferings.
大 清 大 亂 百 姓 磨
Fighting factions caused much agony.
分 派 鬥 爭 苺 萬 般
Abuse was rampant during the 60th year of Kanghsi's reign.
康 熙 六 十 年 清 無 敬
Chu revolted against the Ching and became dominant.
朱 氏 反 清 來 做 大
In 1721, the 60th year of the reign of Emperor Kanghsi,
1721 年 康 熙 六 十 年
Unable to stand paying heavy taxes to Taiwan magistrate
霧 不 了 台 灣 知 府 王 珍 的 苛 稅
Wang Chen, duck farmer Chu Yi-kuei
在 鴨 母 寧 養 鳴 的 朱 一 貴
rose up in arms.
決 定 起 兵 抗 清
Revolutionary forces followed his lead
反 抗 隊 伍 隨 著 他 們
and swiftly captured
迂 速 攻 下
Fengshan, Taiwan, and Chulo counties.
鳳 山 縣 、 台 灣 縣 和 諸 羅 縣
As the resistance movement gained force,
聲 勢 一 再 壯 大
Chu's forces finally captured Tainan Prefecture City.
最 後 他 們 終 於 佔 領 了 府 城
However,
不 遇
after Kuangtung Hakka leader Tu Chun-ying
最 後 由 於 反 抗 隊 伍 中 的
and his forces
廣 東 客 家 勢 力 杜 君 莢
walked out on Chu,
率 領 部 隊 出 走
the largest rebellion against the Ching
使 得 這 個 清 帶 國 治 台 期 間
during its rule of Taiwan
最 大 規 模 的 反 清 事 件
was finally subdued.
終 於 被 消 滅
In fall of the 51st year of the rule of Emperor Chienlung.
乾 隆 五 十 一 清 秋
Lin Shuang-wen's upheaval caused anxiety to civilians.
爾 文 做 亂 害 民 愁
Lin captured Fengchu in Changhua County.
奪 去 鳳 諧 彰 化 縣
18 townships and villages were affected
十 八 鄉 鎮 為 災 愛
In 1786, Lin Shuang-wen of the Earth and Heaven Society
1786 年 天 地 會 的 豪 族 林 爽 文
formed alliances in Changhua to rebel against the Ching Dynasty.
在 彰 化 結 盟 起 兵 抗 清
The rebels had enormous following.
聲 勢 十 分 浩 大
Except Taiwan Prefecture city,
除 了 台 灣 府
other areas were captured.
其 他 地 區 都 被 反 抗 軍 攻 佔
The Ching Empire sent troops to suppress the rebellion,
清 常 國 一 再 增 兵 來 台 灣 鎮 壓
at one time reaching a high of 100,000.
最 高 高 達 十 餘 萬 人
The rebellion, which lasted 16 months,
歷 時 一 年 四 個 月 的 反 清 事 件
finally ended
最 後 也 因 為
when Lin was defeated and captured.
林 爽 文 兵 敗 被 俘 而 結 束
Historically,
從 時 間 上 來 看
armed violence in the early 18th century
十 八 世 紀 初 的 械 鬥
occurred mostly in southern Taiwan.
大 多 數 集 中 在 南 部
During the mid-18th century
十 八 世 紀 中
as immigrants moved north to farm,
移 民 紛 紛 往 北 部 移 壅
the number of armed violence in the north of Choshui River increased.
濂 水 溪 以 北 的 械 鬥 逐 漸 增 多
In the early 19th century
隨 著 十 九 世 紀 初
as areas in Taipei and Yilan developed,
台 北 、 宜 蘭 地 區 的 開 發
the scale and scope of armed violence progressively grew.
械 鬥 的 規 模 和 範 圍 也 逐 步 擴 大
Civil unrests turned into confrontations between
除 了 由 民 變 演 變 成 閩 粵
the Minnan, Kuangtung, and Changchuan peoples.
濘 泉 人 之 間 的 矛 眉 衝 突 外
Between 1684 and 1788,
從 1684 到 1788 的 一 百 年 間
immigrants were not allowed to bring family to Taiwan.
清 常 國 限 制 攜 眷 來 台 的 禁 令
This also caused an imbalance in the demographics then.
也 造 成 台 灣 人 口 結 構 失 衡
Therefore, nomads referred to
因 此 也 出 現 了 一 些
as lo han ka began to appear.
被 稱 為 ﹁ 羅 漢 腳 」 的 遊 民
As cultivation expanded and
後 來 隨 著 台 來 隨 著 台 灣 的 不 斷 開 墓
more immigrants arrived,
移 民 大 量 增 加
conflicts from land disputes worsened.
寸 土 弦 爭 的 衝 突 越 來 越 劇 烈
Armed violence among settlers of different ancestral origins
不 同 祠 籍 移 民 間 的 械 鬥
gradually increased.
也 透 漸 發 生
“Gods fight while the layman suffers.”
﹁ 仙 揉 仙 拼 死 猴 齊 天 」
This kind of saying spoke eloquently about
這 些 俗 語 道 出
partisan armed violence in Taiwan under the Ching rule.
清 代 台 灣 分 類 械 鬥 的 慘 烈
At that time, over 200 villages in Changhua County
當 時 在 彰 化 縣 曾 經 造 成
were affected
超 遇 兩 百 個 村 莊 被 戰 火 波 及
and several hundred people were killed.
數 百 人 喪 生
Armed conflicts of varying scales occurred everywhere
大 大 小 小 的 衛 突 遍 及 各 地
and lasted for years.
長 達 數 年 之 久
As the battles affected the innocent,
戰 火 禍 延 無 辜
farms were left unattended.
田 園 因 此 荒 蕪
Partisan armed violence was the main cause of
分 類 械 鬥 是 清 常 國 統 治 時 期
instability in Taiwan during the Ching rule.
造 成 台 灣 社 會 不 安 的 主 要 原 因
The pain and suffering caused by partisan armed violence
關 於 分 類 械 門 的 憎 慘 情 形
were vividly described
台 灣 旱 期 流 傳 的 歌 謠
in ballads of early Taiwan.
也 有 非 常 生 動 的 描 寫
Behold the white streamer outside the Lungshan Temple.
君 不 見 龍 山 寺 口 白 幡 浮
Chilly wind circles the incense jar.
香 壇 焉 繞 風 颼 颼
Are wives crying for husbands or fathers for their sons?
不 知 妻 哭 夫 刈 父 哭 子
Their cries touch the heaven, that morns for their lost.
但 聞 哭 聲 霞 天 天 為 愛
As waves of Han immigrants arrived,
漢 人 移 民 一 波 接 一 波 登 岸
misfortune befell
原 來 住 在 島 上 的 原 住 民
the aborigines living in the island.
器 運 卻 跟 隨 而 來
Han-Kavalan county prosecutor Ko Pei-yuan
漢 人 官 員 囑 瑪 蘭 通 判 柯 培 元
often saw Pingpu aborigines
在 官 府 申 曜 見
being abused in the government building.
平 埔 人 被 欺 壓 的 處 境
He wrote the poem Shu Fan Ko:
寬 下 了 古 詩 ﹁ 熟 番 歌 」
“People think raw barbarians are as fierce as the tiger.
人 畏 生 番 猛 如 虎
People mock cultured barbarians as wretched as mud.
人 欺 熟 番 賤 如 土
In Taiwan,
我 看 到 台 灣
the lands of mountain aborigines
原 來 住 在 山 上 的 居 氏
were being seized by the Han.
土 地 被 漢 人 侵 奪
Due to language barriers,
困 為 言 語 不 通
the aborigines could not relate the incidents
他 們 很 難 將 事 件 原 委
to the local officials.
告 訴 地 方 官 員
The officials also sided with the Han Chinese,
官 方 又 往 往 袒 護 漢 人
making it more difficult for the aborigines to seek justice.
更 使 他 們 的 冤 屈 難 以 伸 張
When leasing farmlands from the Pingpu people,
漢 人 向 平 埔 族 租 耕 土 地 時
the Han Chinese took advantage of
利 用 他 們 沒 有 文 字
the illiterate aborigines
不 識 漢 字 這 個 弱 點
to draft lease contracts in their favor.
故 意 在 契 約 上 動 手 腳
Instead of the lease period, the Han Chinese would
漢 人 將 有 年 限 的 租 耕
indicate that the land was sold to the Han,
寫 成 是 永 久 賣 給 漢 人
and let the aborigines sign the contracts.
再 讓 平 埔 族 人 畫 押
When the aborigines filed complaints with the
以 後 如 果 發 生 爭 基
government during disputes,
平 埔 族 人 向 官 府 控 告 時
the Han Chinese connived with interpreters to manipulate
漢 人 就 勾 結 通 事 類 倒 是 非
facts and cause the aborigines to lose lawsuits
使 得 平 埔 族 人 敗 訴
and their lands
喪 失 土 地
The Han Chinese learned that the Pingpu people
漢 人 發 現 平 埔 族
were very scared of corpses and dirty things
非 常 害 害 怕 死 屍 與 髒 與 體 東 西
so they deliberately left
就 故 意 在 田 間
unclean things in the farm
丟 棄 這 些 不 潔 淨 的 東 西
to scare the aborigines
讓 他 們 害 怕 不 吉 利
and make them leave.
棄 地 而 去
While they cultivated and developed Taiwan,
漢 人 移 民 在 操 拓 台 灣 的 遇 程 中
the Han immigrants used deception and force
利 用 款 騙 或 強 迫 的 手 段
to acquire vast areas of lands
從 原 住 民 的 世 居 地
from the aborigines.
取 得 大 量 的 土 地
This reduced the aborigines' means of livelihood
造 成 平 埔 族 人 生 活 空 間 的 菱 縮
and threatened their survival.
和 生 存 威 脢 的 厄 運
Before the Han Chinese came,
漢 人 移 入 台 灣 以 前
the Pingpu aborigines
遷 徒 本 來 就 是
led nomadic lives.
平 埔 各 社 之 間 的 生 活 方 式 之 一
During the Ching rule,
清 朝 統 治 時 期
the waves of Han Chinese immigrants
大 批 漢 人 移 氏
brought immense cultural impacts
帶 給 了 島 上 的 平 地 原 住 民
on the aborigines.
極 大 的 文 化 衝 擊
The Siraya tribe in the north was the first to be affected.
世 居 南 部 的 西 拉 雅 族 首 當 其 衝
The Pingpu aborigines in the west
台 灣 西 部 地 區 的 平 埔 人
continued to move until
不 斷 地 遷 從
there was almost nowhere else to go.
幾 乎 無 路 可 退
Most in the end had to adopt
大 部 分 只 好 接 受 漢 文 化
Chinese culture and use Chinese names,
採 用 漢 人 的 堂 號 、 姓 氏
and the aborigines gradually
困 此 逐 漸 失 去
lost their names and dialects
原 住 民 的 名 字 和 母 語
Only a few, such as
只 有 少 數
the Siraya and Kavalan,
像 西 拉 雅 人 與 囑 瑪 蘭 人
who had moved to remote places
困 為 遷 從 到 比 較 偏 遠 的 地 方
and avoided threats from the Han Chinese,
躲 避 漢 人 的 威 股
were able to keep some of their culture,
勉 強 保 留 住 少 許 自 己 的 文 化
customs, and traditions.
和 傳 統 習 俗
In the early Ching period,
清 代 早 期
Han immigrants were forbidden to bring family to Taiwan.
漢 人 移 民 攜 眷 限 制 重 重
Many single Han males
許 多 單 身 漢
married Pingpu women.
也 都 娶 了 平 埔 族 女 子 為 妻
Doing so, they not only were able to marry,
既 解 決 了 婚 姻 問 題
but also acquired
也 順 利 取 得 了
rights to the lands of the aborigines.
平 埔 族 的 土 地 控 制 權
The Pingpu people lived in a maternal society.
平 埔 族 比 較 傾 向 母 系 社 會
They practiced matrilocal marriage
所 以 他 們 的 婚 姻 形 態
similar to some of the Han Chinese.
類 似 漢 人 的 招 贅 婚
In a Siraya marriage,
西 拉 雅 人 的 婚 姻
the couple refer to each other as kan chi...
夫 妻 雙 方 互 稱 ﹁ 牽 手 」
No wedding ceremony was required.
結 婚 時 沒 有 任 何 婚 禮 儀 式
As long as the dowry was accepted,
只 要 女 方 接 受 男 方 所 贈 的 嫁 妝
the marriage would be consummated.
婚 姻 立 即 成 立
The groom could move into the bride's home that evening.
當 晚 新 郎 就 可 住 進 女 方 家 裡
Today among Taiwanese,
現 在 的 台 灣 人
a husband refers to his wife as kan chiu,
丈 夫 稱 妻 子 為 ﹁ 牽 手 」
which originated from the aborigine wedding tradition.
其 實 是 源 自 平 埔 人 的 婚 姻 儀 式
This is also an instance where the Pingpu dialect
也 是 台 灣 話 參 雜 平 埔 族 語 言 的
is assimilated into the Taiwanese dialect
一 個 明 顳 例 子
Through intermarriage,
漢 人 經 由 通 婚
the Han Chinese
和 島 上 居 住 海 岸 平 地 的
bonded with the Pingpu people
平 埔 族 原 住 民
living in coastal areas.
在 血 統 上 互 相 融 合
“A mainland husband without a mainland wife”
﹁ 有 唐 山 公 無 唐 山 媽 」
is a Taiwanese saying
這 句 台 灣 俗 語 f8
that best describes the
陽 這 種
bonding and assimilation of ethnic groups.
族 群 重 組 與 融 合 的 最 佳 寫 照
The Pingpu culture
平 埔 族 文 化
has assimilated into the Han culture,
其 實 已 經 被 融 入 漢 人 文 化 之 中
and the Pingpu blood run through many of today's Taiwanese.
甚 至 是 現 在 台 灣 人 血 緣 的 一 部 份
After the Lin Shuang-wen incident,
林 爽 文 事 件 之 後
to prevent reoccurrence of civil unrest
台 灣 各 地
many areas in Taiwan
為 了 防 止 民 變 再 度 發 生
constructed city walls made of clay.
紛 紛 改 建 土 牆 城 垣
The emergence of city walls
土 牆 城 垣 的 出 現
reflected the renewed mindset of the Ching Dynasty
反 昧 出 清 嘯 清 常 國 對 統 治 台 灣
in its rule of Taiwan.
有 了 新 的 認 知
Taiwan was no longer an island of barbarians.
不 再 視 台 灣 台 灣 為 化 外 小 島
Taiwan also started to prosper
台 灣 也 困 為 海 上 貿 易 的 興 監
due to increased sea trades.
逐 漸 繁 榮
After a long period,
經 過 了 一 段 漫 長 的 歲 月
Taiwan had evolved from the early-day immigrant society
台 灣 已 經 從 早 期 的 移 民 社 會
into a localized society
發 展 成 在 地 化
with business potentials.
而 且 具 商 業 潛 力 的 社 會
A Taiwanese saying refers to three places:
有 句 台 灣 俗 語
Tainan Prefecture City, Lukang, and Bangka.
﹁ 一 府 二 鹿 三 艋 船 」
These were the three major ports bustling
便 是 形 容 當 時 商 船 雲 集
with commercial activities.
生 意 興 隆 的 港 口
Since 1683,
顯 示 自 1683 年 以 來
the busy ports have been testament to the frequent
台 灣 海 峽 貿 易
and population movement across the Strait.
與 人 口 移 動 的 頻 繁
The desolate world Yu Yung-he saw during his time
郎 永 河 當 年 眼 見 的 蠻 荒 世 界
was now part of the past.
已 經 成 為 歷 史 的 留 痕
After more than 100 years of Ching rule,
台 灣 在 清 帶 國 統 治 一 百 多 年 後
the population in the plains was how close to two million.
平 地 的 人 口 已 經 接 近 兩 百 萬 人
Aborigines living outside the Ching-ruled areas
清 國 統 治 區 以 外 的 原 住 民
also increased to over 100,000.
也 有 十 多 萬 人
They maintained their lifestyle,
他 們 維 持 著 自 己 的 生 活 型 態
and lived in a closed, self-sufficient society.
形 成 了 一 個 封 閉 自 足 的 社 會
This was just before the European imperial powers
然 而 這 時 正 是 歐 洲 帝 國 勢 力
began its invasion of the Ching Empire.
大 舉 進 遇 清 常 國 的 前 夕
Located in the southeastern border of the Ching Empire,
台 灣 位 居 常 國 的 東 南 海 疆
Taiwan's fate
她 的 命 運
would again undergo a drastic change.
也 再 次 面 臨 重 要 的 改 變
In 1840, dispute between the Ching Dynasty and Britain
1840 年 大 清 與 大 莫 帝 國
culminated in the Opium War.
困 為 鴉 片 問 題 開 啟 戰 端
From 1841 to 1842,
1841 年 與 1842 年
two British ships attacking
兩 艘 英 國 船 艦 分 別 進 犯
Chilung Harbor and Taan Harbor in Taiwan
台 灣 的 雞 籠 港 和 大 安 港
were defeated by the stationed troops.
被 駐 台 官 兵 擊 敗
More than 100 British soldiers were captured.
船 上 官 兵 一 百 多 人 被 俘 虜
Apart from 30-odd soldiers who died from illness,
除 了 三 十 多 人 病 死
the remaining 139 Indian mercenaries
其 餘 一 百 三 十 九 名 印 度 傷 兵
were beheaded in public
在 1842 年 8 月 13 日
outside the city's north gate
被 常 往 府 城 北 門 外 的 刑 場
on the 13th of the 8th lunar month, 1842.
斬 首 示 真
Many years later,
一 位 親 臨 現 場 的 漢 人
A Han Chinese witness
在 多 年 以 後
recounted to a foreign reporter
曾 經 對 一 名 外 國 記 者
the horrendous mass killing
描 述 當 年
during that time.
這 個 殘 酷 的 大 屠 殺 事 件
Yes,
是 的
I remember that day.
我 記 得 那 一 天
It was a dark day for Taiwan.
是 臺 灣 黑 暗 的 日 子
The execution started
他 們 在 上 午 九 點 工 右
at about 9:00 a.m.
就 開 始 處 決
and ended at noon.
大 約 中 午 時 號 結 束
There were government officials and thousands of onlookers.
現 場 有 官 府 的 人 和 數 千 名 百 姚
The sky had grown dark
但 還 沒 全 部 斬 首 完
before the execution ended.
天 室 已 烏 雪 密 佈
There was thunder and lightning,
隨 即 雷 電 交 加
and it rained for three successive days.
狂 風 大 雨 連 續 下 了 三 天
Ah!
丫 SJ
It was the heaven condemning the killing of foreigners.
那 是 斬 外 國 人 的 天 譴
The brutal action by the Taiwan government
台 灣 當 局 的 殘 酷 行 動
was to avenge the taking of
是 為 了 報 復 鴉 片 戰 爭 時
Hsiamen by British fleet during the Opium War.
莫 國 軍 艦 奪 取 廈 門
Although defeated
雖 然 莫 軍 在 次 戰 場
in this battle at Taiwan,
對 台 灣 的 軍 事 行 動 失 利
the British were victorious
但 是 在 主 戰 場 的 大 陸 沿 海
in major battles along the coasts of China.
卻 得 到 全 面 的 勝 利
The Ching Dynasty was forced
清 常 國 被 迪
to sign the first unequal treaty
簽 訂 了 中 國 墩 史 上 的
in China's history.
第 一 個 不 平 等 條 約
In the Treaty of Nanjing,
在 南 京 條 約 中
Hong Kong was ceded to the British.
將 香 港 割 讓 給 英 國
In 1858, the British-French
1858 年
Alliance forces once again defeated the Ching army.
莫 法 聯 軍 再 次 打 敗 清 國
The Ching Dynasty signed the Treaty of Tienchin
清 常 國 與 英 法 各 國
with the U.K., France, and other countries.
簽 訂 天 津 條 約
The treaty opened
清 國 依 照 合 約
Taiwan's four major ports:
開 放 台 灣 的 安 平 、 淡 水 、 雞 籠 、 打 狗 等
Anping, Tamsui, Chilung, and Takou to foreign trade.
四 大 港 口 與 外 國 通 商
Closed for over 100 years,
在 封 閉 了 一 百 多 年 後
Taiwan's gate was open once again.
台 灣 的 門 戶 再 一 次 被 打 開
Western and Japanese merchants, adventurers,
西 方 和 日 本 的 商 人 、 冒 險 家
and missionaries came to Taiwan.
和 傳 教 士 紛 紛 來 到 台 灣
The western world brought to Taiwan a new civilization.
西 方 世 界 帶 來 新 的 文 明 洗 禮
Taiwan would meet the West
台 灣 又 將 重 新 和 西 方 相 遇
and become connected to the world scene once again.
和 世 界 接 軌